For this assignment we'll be using the
この課題では
empty scene in the robot lab.
Robot Lab での空のシーンを使用します。
Open the empty scene and then to make
空のシーンを開いて、その中で
sure that we maintain our empty scene
空のシーンを保持できることを確実にするため
go to File - Save Scene As
メニューから File - Save Scene As を選択して
save it in to the Scenes folder
Scenes フォルダに保存して
and we'll call this Bouncing Ball.
BouncingBall という名前にします。
As usual Unity takes you straight into the
いつもと同様に Unity は先ほど保存したばかり
scene that you've just saved, so we're now
のシーンに移動するので、
working in the bouncing ball scene.
現在は BouncingBall のシーンで作業しています。
A good first thing to do in Unity is
Unity で最初に行うと良いこととして、
make the classic bouncing ball that you
他のソフトウェアで作成したかもしれない
may have done in other pieces of software.
ありがちな BouncingBall を作成することです。
In the models folder we have some
Models フォルダにはいくつかの
primitive shapes, such as the spherical
プリミティブ形状があり、Sphere 形の
'samoflange' and the cubic
samoflange および Cube 形の
'power cube', as well as a number of other
powerCube や、その他いくつかの異なる
different assets.
アセットがあります。
From the models folder, drag and drop
Models フォルダから prop_samoflange を
the 'prop samoflange' object in to the scene.
シーン上にドラッグ&ドロップします。
Remember that you can use the translate tool
位置調整ツールを使用して
to select and move it around.
選択して移動できることを忘れないで下さい。
This can be done by dragging the handles
これはハンドルをドラッグしたり、
or by dragging the planes on the object.
オブジェクトの表面をドラッグすることで実現できます。
You should notice that I'm using the F key
F キーを使用してオブジェクトにフォーカスをあてるだけでなく
to focus on that object and move the scene
シーンビューを動かして
view in to focus on it too.
フォーカスがあたることに気づくはずです。
To make sure that our object is lit by our
オブジェクトは動的ライティングにより
dynamic lights make sure that the layer
samoflange のレイヤーが
of the samoflange is set to Dynamic Objects.
Dynamic Objects にセットされていることを確かめて下さい。
Now you should see that our object is
これでオブジェクトが綺麗にライティングされていて、
nicely lit and in the mesh renderer
さらに Mesh Renderer の中で
we can also check 'Use Light Probes'.
Use Light Probes をチェックできます。
Now our object will be properly lit
シーンの中でオブジェクトは
within the scene.
適切にライティングされます。
Next we'll add a rigidbody component
次に Rigidbody コンポーネントを追加するので
so click the Add Component button
インスペクタの Add Component ボタンをクリックして
on the inspector and go to Physics -
Physics - Rigidbody を
Rigidbody.
選択します。
However we can't use a rigidbody
Rigidbody はコライダを使用せずに
without a collider.
使うことが出来ません。
So let's go to Add Component - Physics -
このため Add Component - Physics とクリックして
Sphere Collider. This gives our spherical
Sphere Collider を選択します。これで Sphere 形の
object a bounding area and if we zoom in
オブジェクトに跳ねるエリアが出来て
you should see that there's a green outline
ズームインすると緑色の枠線が
going around it. Looking at the rigidbody
表示されます。Rigidbody をみると
you can see that we have
プロパティとして
properties for mass, drag, etcetera
質量 (Mass) および抵抗 (Drag) などがあり、
and also a checkbox for Use Gravity.
さらに Use Gravity のためのチェックボックスがあります。
By default this is checked and that's
デフォルトでこのチェックボックスは有効化されていて
exactly what we want to do here as well,
ここで行いたいことと同様です。
and what we'll also do is effect the kind of
さらにこのオブジェクトに与える
friction that we want this object to have.
摩擦の効果を設定します。
By default if I press play now
デフォルトでは、ここで Play を押下すると
the object will fall to the floor
オブジェクトは地面に落ちます。
but what we want to do is add in a friction
しかしここで行いたいことは摩擦も
response too. This is handled
与えることです。これは
by the physics material on the collider.
コライダの 物理マテリアル (Physics Material) によりハンドリングされます。
So we're going to make a new physics material
新しい物理マテリアルを作成するので
so I'm going to select the Assets folder
Assets フォルダを選択したうえで
and then we'll make a folder for this,
物理マテリアルのための作成していきます。
so click the Create button and choose Folder
Create ボタンをクリックして Folder を選択して
and make a new folder in which to store
物理マテリアルを格納する新規のフォルダを
physic materials.
作成します。
Then because we want to create this
次に、このフォルダの中に
physics material inside that folder
物理マテリアルを作成するために
select the folder then go back to Create
フォルダを選択したうえで Create をクリックして
and choose Physics Material.
Physics Material を選択します。
This creates it inside the folder.
これにより物理マテリアルがこのフォルダの中に作成されます。
And as soon as you create it you can then
そして作成が終わったらすぐに名前をつけて
name it, and you should name it Bouncy.
Bouncy という名前をつけます。
Because that's what we're going to create - a bouncy ball.
名前どおりにこれから跳ねるボールを作成します。
Before setting up this asset I'm going
このアセットをセットアップする前に
to apply it to the object so that we don't
忘れないうちにオブジェクトへアタッチします。
forget later. So reselect the
このために prop_samoflange を再選択して
prop samoflange and then drag Bouncy
Bouncy を
from the project panel and drop it on
プロジェクト パネルからドラッグして
to the physic material setting
インスペクタ上のコンポーネントの
in the component in the inspector.
物理マテリアルの設定にドロップします。
Now reselect the asset in the project panel
次にプロジェクト パネルのアセットを再選択して
and we'll take a look at it's settings.
設定をみていきます。
You can see here that a key one that we
調整をすべきパラメータは
want to play with is Bounciness.
Bounciness (弾性係数) です。
And I'm going to set this to 0.8.
この値に 0.8 をセットします。
Now if I press play what you'll see
Play ボタンを押下すると、
is that it bounces to a halt.
跳ねずにすぐ停止します。
The reason for this is Bounce Combine.
止まる原因は Bounce Combine です。
Because what this does is average the
このパラメータによりオブジェクトと
friction on the object and the
その衝突相手である床との
object that it's colliding with - the floor.
摩擦を平均化します。
So whilst I've set this to 0.8
つまり、パラメータを 0.8 にセットしたものの、
because it's averaging the two, what we're
二つの値を平均化しているため、
actually getting is 0.4.
実際には 0.4 になるということです。
So what we'll do is set Bounce Combine
やるべきことは Bounce Combine を
to maximum. Do that now.
Maximum に設定することです。
Then you can test out again by pressing play.
次に Play ボタンをクリックして再度テストが出来ます。
And now that you can see that it has
みてのとおり、跳ねる強さが
more bounce to it.
ましています。
But if we want it to keep bouncing forever
もし永久に跳ね続けてほしい場合は
we should set Bounciness to a value of 1.
Bounciness の値を 1 にします。
And we're going to make things a bit more
それではもっと面白いことをしましょう。
interesting now. With our object
オブジェクトを
roughly in the middle of the scene
おおよそシーンの真ん中に置いて
reselect it and choose the Translate tool.
再選択したうえで位置調整ツールを選択します。
Remember you can use W on the keyboard
キーボードの W キーを使用すれば
to select that tool at any time.
いつでも位置調整ツールを選択できることを覚えとくと便利です。
I'm going to drag it up so that it's a little
少し高い位置に来るようにドラッグして
high and then from the Models folder
Models フォルダか
I'm going to locate my bench.
使用する bench をみつけます。
So grab PropBenchWork
PropBenchWork をクリックして
and drag that in to the scene.
シーン上にドラッグします。
Yet again I'm going to put it on the dynamic
ここでもレイヤーは
objects layer and I'm going
Dynamic Objects として
to go in to the mesh renderer and
Mesh Renderer にて
choose Use Light Probes so that it's
Use Light Probes チェックボックスを有効化して
nicely lit by our dynamic lights.
綺麗な動的ライティングが行われるようにします。
Then what I'm going to do is add a collider
次に行うことはコライダの追加であり、
because we're going to make our samoflange ball
samoflange ボールが
bounce off of the bench.
Bench から跳ねて落ちるようにします。
So I'm going to go to Add Component - Physics
メニューから Add Component - Physics を選択して
and nice and simply I'm just going to add
簡単に素敵なプリミティブ ボックスコライダを
a primitive box collider to this.
これにアタッチします。
Then hover your mouse over the scene view
次にマウスをシーンビュー上に置いたまま
and press F to focus on the object
F キーを押下してオブジェクトにフォーカスして
so that we can see it a little bit closer.
より近くから表示します。
Note that at various times I am holding
ドラッグするときに何回か
down the Alt key on the keyboard to orbit
キーボード上の Alt キーを押したままにしている
around as I drag.
ことに注意して下さい。
Now I'm going to go to the Hand tool,
次にハンドツールに移動して、
to effectively hide the translate handles
要するに位置調整ツールを見えない状態にして
and I'm going to hold down Shift to adjust
コライダの境界を調整するのに
the boundaries of the collider.
Shift キーを押したままにします。
The reason I'm doing this
こうする理由はコライダの
is because I don't want it to bounce off
上部から
of the top of the collider here.
このように跳ねて落ちてほしくないためです。
I'd rather it bounced off of the surface.
それなら表面から跳ねるほうが良いです。
So all I'm going to do now is hold down Shift
そこで次は Shift キーを押したままにして
and drag the top one
最上部のものをドラッグして
until it's roughly in line with the top of
workbench のメッシュとおおよそ同じ高さとなるまで
the work bench mesh.
ドラッグします。
Now what we're going to do is go back
次にやることは
to the Translate tool
位置調整ツールに戻って
and I'm going to drag this upward,
上方向にドラッグして、
something like that.
このような形にします。
And now what I'm going to do is
次にやることは
tilt it at an angle. So I'm going to go
角度を傾けることです。つまり
to my Rotate tool,
キーボード上の E キーがショートカットとなっている
which remember is E on the keyboard,
回転ツールに移動して
and I'm going to tilt it
傾けて、
something like that.
このような形にします。
Then all I'm going to do is switch to
次にやることは
an overhead view, so using the View
真上からのビューに切り替えるために
gizmo in the top right of the scene view
シーンビューな右上にあるギズモを使用して
click on the green Y axis spoke.
緑色のY 軸の線をクリックします。
And then I'm going to reselect my
次に Sphere である prop_samoflange を
spherical prop samoflange
再選択して
and I'm going to get my view in order
必要なビューに遷移して
and then I'm going to drag with the
位置調整ツールを使って
Translate tool until it's over the top.
真上に来るまでドラッグし続けます。
Note that I'm still in a perspective view
現在は Perspective ビューにいて
and if I want to go to an orthographic view
もし Orthographic ビューに遷移したい場合は
I can click the cube in the middle, like that.
次のようにキューブを真ん中でクリックします。
So now if I zoom in
これでズームインすると
I can see exactly whether it's over the top.
ちょうど真上かどうか判別できます。
And I'm going to keep using the Translate tool
再度、位置調整ツールを使用して
to position it where I want it.
おきたい場所に配置します。
And remember that we can rotate round
回転してサイド ビューに
to side-on views as well to ensure that
切り替えることで
we're getting it in exactly the right place
ちょうど配置できているか確認ができて、
and keep rotating around until we're happy.
満足できる回転位置となるまで調整ができます。
Then I'm going to click on the white cube
次に Gizmo の真ん中にある
in the middle of the gizmo to go back
白いキューブをクリックして
to my perspective view.
Perspective ビューに戻ることができます。
Now all I'm going to do is press play.
次に Play ボタンを押します。
And as you can see our samoflange ball
みてのとおり samoflange ボールは
keeps bouncing around all over the environment.
画面中を跳ね続けます。
And that's it.
これで完了です。
Remember to save your scene, and keep
シーンを保存して、
experimenting with the different values
物理マテリアル アセットの
in the physic material asset to get
様々な値で調整をしてみて
different effects,
色々な効果を試して下さい。
or refer to the Physic Materials lesson
あるいは、より詳細を知るために
for more information.
Physic Materials のレッスンを参照して下さい。 (翻訳:gamesonytablet)